Sync and corrections by n17t01
www.addic7ed.com
中文字幕：@SaltyEggPain
宇    宙
时空探险之旅
第 5 集
藏在光中的秘密
Hiding in the Light
The age and size of the cosmos
宇宙的年龄和大小
are written in light.
都被记录在光中
The nature of beauty and
the substance of the stars,
美丽的大自然和恒星的物质
the laws of space and time...
时空的定律
they were there all along,
原本就存在
but we never saw them...
但我们过去未能发现
until we devised
a more powerful way of seeing.
直到我们拥有了更为强大的观察方式
The story of this awakening
has many beginnings
这种觉醒的故事有很多的开始
and no ending.
却不会结束
Its heroes come from many times
and places--
从不同时间和地方涌现出许多的英雄
an Ancient Chinese philosopher,
中国古代的哲人
a wizard who amazed the caliphs
of 11th-century Iraq,
令11世纪伊拉克穆斯林统治者叹服的奇才
a poor German orphan enslaved
to a harsh master.
被苛刻奴役的德国可怜孤儿
Each one brought us
a little closer
每一位都带领我们前进一小步
to unlocking the secrets
hidden in light.
去解开藏在光中的秘密
Most of their names
are forever lost to us,
大多数的名字都已经被遗忘了
but somewhere, long ago,
someone glanced up
但在某处  很久前  某人的匆匆一瞥
to see light perform
one of its magic tricks.
注意到了光线展示出的神奇
Who knows?
谁知道呢
Maybe that quirk of light
或许光线的偶然作为
inspired the very first artist.
为第一位艺术家带来了灵感
Where did all this come from?
这些都是怎么来的
How did we evolve
from small wandering bands
我们是如何从小量聚居的
of hunters and gatherers living
beneath the stars
采集者和猎人 进化而来的
to become the builders
of a global civilization?
成为世界文明的缔造者
How did we get from there
to here?
中间的过程是怎样的
There's no one answer.
没有统一的答案
Climate change,
the domestication of fire,
气候的变化  学会控制火
the invention of tools,
language, agriculture
工具的发明  语言  耕种
all played a role.
都有各自的功劳
Maybe there was
something else, too.
或许还有其他的
In China,
more than 2,000 years ago,
中国  2000多年前
a philosopher named Mo Tze
is said to have observed
一位名叫 墨子 的哲人 据说发现了
that light could be made
to paint a picture
光线可以在密闭的宝库中
inside a locked treasure room.
产生图像 （小孔成像）
This was the description
of the first camera...
这描述的就是第一台照相机
the camera obscura,
暗箱
the prototype of all
image-forming cameras,
所有成像照相机的原型
including the one that's
bringing you this picture.
包括给你带来图像的这台摄像机
Taking advantage of this funny
thing that light does
利用光线这种有趣的现象
resulted in what could be
called the first movie.
催生了首部的电影
Mo Tze, master of light, worked
against all forms of darkness.
墨子 光线大师  专治各种黑暗
A military genius
军事天才
who only used his talents
to prevent violence,
以智抑暴
he was legendary for traveling
他最著名的成就是
among the kingdoms
of the warring states,
穿行于战乱的国家间
employing ingenious strategies
运用巧妙的策略
to talk kings out
of going to war.
劝导各方休战
He was one of the first
to dream of universal love
他是兼爱的倡导者
and an end to poverty
and other forms of inequality;
提倡消灭统治者带给人们的
of government for the people...
贫困与不公
and to argue against
blind obedience
批判对于宗教和权威的盲从
to ritual and authority.
In his writings, you can find
在他的著作中  你能发现
early stirrings
of the scientific approach.
科学探索的早期萌芽
By Mo Tze's time, the Chinese
had already been recording
到墨子那个年代  中国人已经开始
their thoughts in books
for at least a thousand years.
用书籍记录他们的思想 至少上千年了
Still, our knowledge of him
is only fragmentary.
但我们对他的了解 依然仅是只字片语
It consists largely
of the collection of essays
通过许多由他和他的追随者
attributed to him
and his disciples.
所著的文集而来
In one of them,
entitled "Against Fate,"
其中一篇 题为《非命》
a three-pronged test
for every doctrine is proposed.
立论一定要有三项标准 （故言必有三表）
Question its basis--
推究来历 （有本之者）
ask if it can be verified
是否可以由
by the sights and senses
of common people--
普通人的观感再次验证的 （有原之者）
ask how it is to be applied
是否可以推广
and if it will benefit
the greatest number.
并使大多数人受益 （有用之者）
Mo Tze was extremely popular,
墨子的思想流传很广
but a few hundred years
after his death,
但他身后的数百年
Qin Shi Huang,
the first emperor,
秦始皇  第一位皇帝
and unifier of China,
took power.
统一了中国  独揽大权
He took a continent
and turned it into a nation
他将一片大陆变成了一个国家
that now bears his name... China.
这个现在依然受他影响的国度  中国
Most of us know Emperor Qin
for the army of 7,000
我们大多数人对他的了解
terra cotta warriors
that guard his tomb.
来自守卫陵墓的7000件兵马俑
In Emperor Qin's drive
在秦始皇的领导下
to consolidate
his far-flung empire,
为了巩固辽阔的帝国
he took drastic measures
他采取极端的手段
to standardize everything
within it.
为所有事物都建立了标准
This included mandating
a single coinage,
包括 铸造单一货币
making uniform all weights
and measures,
统一度量衡
the widths of carts and roads,
as well as the precise way
车辆与道路的宽度 （车同轨） 还有
the Chinese language was
to be written,
中文书写形式的规范 （书同文）
including what you were
allowed to write and think.
也包括了什么是可以写 什么是可以想的
Emperor Qin's philosophy--
the only one permitted--
秦始皇的哲学 唯一他认可的
was called "legalism,"
称之 法家学说
which is just what
it sounded like,
就如同它的字面意思
do as the law says... or else.
遵纪守法 否则呵呵
It's a philosophy that's
not highly conducive
这种哲学理论对于质疑权威
to questioning authority.
不是十分有利
...that all the books of
the hundred schools of thought
百家思想的书籍
shall be be burned,
统统烧掉
that anyone who uses history
to criticize the present
以古讽今者
shall have his family executed.
全家处斩
The works of
MoTze and Confucius
墨子和孔子的著作
and other philosophers
were destroyed
还有其他哲人的作品
in the world's first
book burning.
尽毁于世界历史上首次的焚书
Hundreds of scholars
bravely resisted
数百名书生英勇抵抗
by trying to preserve
the forbidden books.
试图保护这些禁书
They were buried alive
in the capitol.
在首都（咸阳）将他们活埋 （坑儒）
Science needs the light
of free expression to flourish.
科学需要有自由的表达才能繁荣发展
It depends on the fearless
questioning of authority,
需要无畏的质疑权威
the open exchange of ideas.
开放的交流思想
Sparks of curiosity
in the writings of Mo Tze
墨子和他的追随者们所记载的
and his disciples were
effectively stomped out.
突发奇想都被抹杀了
It would be another thousand
years before the next movie.
影片的再次出现 已是另一个千年之后
Luckily, our Ship
of the Imagination
幸运的是 我们的想象之舟
can take us anywhere
in space... and time.
可以带我们去任何的空间和时间
The ancient Chinese
and Greeks observed
中国和希腊的古人发现
that light could be made
光线可以展现出各种神奇
to do wonderful things--
but no one asked that question
但是却没人去问
favored by small children
and geniuses alike. Why?
小孩子和天才们喜欢问的问题  为什么
Until a thousand years ago...
直到一千年前
In the city of Basra, Iraq,
伊拉克的巴斯拉城
there lived
another master of light.
生活着另一位光线大师
Ibn al-Hazen had a passionate
desire to understand nature.
海桑极度渴望了解自然
He questioned everything,
他对一切都有疑问
especially those things that
everyone else took for granted.
特别是那些别人认为理所应当的事情
"How do we see?" he asked.
我们怎么能看到  他问
Some of the great authorities
who came before him
有些在他之前的伟大权威
had taught that rays come out
of our eyes and travel
认为光线从我们的眼中出发
to the objects we see
before returning to our eyes.
在物体上反射 然后返回我们的眼中
But al-Hazen reasoned that
the stars were too far distant
但海桑不认同 理由是恒星离我们那么远
for something in our eyes
to travel all the way to them
什么东西可以从我们眼中射向星星
and back in the blink
of an eye.
并在一眨眼的时间内返回
Excellent reasoning,
but al-Hazen didn't stop there.
很有道理  但海桑并未止步
He searched for ways to compel
nature to divulge her secrets.
他绞尽脑汁探索大自然的奥秘
His culture was open
to new ideas and questioning.
当时他的文化对于新的见解与质疑是开放的态度
It was the golden age
of science
那是科学发展的黄金时代
in the Islamic world.
在伊斯兰世界
One that stretched from Cordoba
in Spain
伊斯兰世界从西班牙的科索瓦
all the way to Samarkand
in Central Asia.
一直延伸到中亚的撒马尔罕
Christian and Jewish scholars
were honored guests
基督教和犹太教的学者被敬为上宾
at the research institutes
of Baghdad, Cairo,
在开罗  巴格达的研究机构
and other Islamic capitols.
和其他伊斯兰世界的中心
Instead of burning books,
the caliphs sent emissaries
不同于秦始皇  哈里发们派遣使者
（哈里发是穆斯林统治者的称号）
around the world
in search of books.
在世界各地搜集书籍
The caliphs lavishly funded
projects to translate, study,
哈里发们大量的资助将这些书籍
and preserve them
for future generations.
翻译 研究  并保存  流传后世
Much of the light of Ancient
Greek science would have been
多亏了他们的努力  许多古希腊科学家的
permanently extinguished
without their efforts.
成果才得以保存
The reawakening to science
that took place in Europe,
对科学的狂热在欧洲再次兴起
hundreds of years later,
was kindled by a flame
发生在几百年后 多亏了伊斯兰学者和
that had been long tended
科学家对这些文献的
by Islamic scholars
and scientists.
精心呵护
The Arabs also imported ideas
from India to the West,
阿拉伯人将新思想由印度传入西方
including the so-called
Arabic numerals
包括所谓的  阿拉伯数字
that we all use today,
我们至今都在使用
and the concept of zero...
还有数字0
which comes in handy
确实很方便
when you want to write
"billions and billions."
特别是当你书写 几十亿又几十亿时
Arabic astronomy was
so influential,
阿拉伯天文学十分具有影响力
that we still call most
of the bright stars
我们至今依然用阿拉伯语名字来称呼
by their Arabic names.
那些明亮的恒星
And the "al's" in algebra,
algorithm, alchemy, and alcohol
代数  算法  炼金术  酒精 这些英语单词中的 al
are just some
of the traces left
也是佐证
from the time when Arabic
was the language of science.
当时阿拉伯语是科学界的通用语
In the 11th century,
Ibn al-Hazen set about trying
11世纪时  海桑准备尝试
to test his ideas about light
and how we see.
验证他关于光和我们如何看见的理论
So we devised an experiment
to determine how light moves.
我们设计了一套实验测定光线如何移动
We erected a tent
in full daylight
我们在烈日下支起一顶帐篷
and sealed it tightly so that
only a single ray of light
将它完全密封 只允许一束光穿过
could pierce its inner darkness.
射入内部的黑暗中
With little more than his brains
他用他的智慧
and a straight
piece of wood-- a ruler--
加上一件笔直的木质工具  尺子
al-Hazen had accomplished
a great leap forward
海桑完成了一次科学历史上
in the history of science.
伟大的跨越
He discovered that
light moves in straight lines.
他发现光线呈直线运动
But he was just getting started.
这只是开始
Al-Hazen figured out that
the key to forming any image--
海桑总结出成像的关键
whether you're talking about
an eye or camera obscura--
不论 眼睛还是照相机暗箱
is a small opening to restrict
the light that can enter
都是通过控制光线进入
an otherwise darkened chamber.
黑暗内室的小孔
That aperture
excludes the chaos
光圈将我们周遭繁杂无关的
of extraneous light rays
that surround us.
光线排除在外
The smaller the aperture,
光圈越小
the fewer directions
that light can come from.
进入的光线角度范围越小
And that makes
the image sharper.
使图像更清晰
So instead of being blinded
by the light,
从而不至于让光线致盲
we can see everything
it has to show us.
我们可以分辨光线呈现的图像
Al-Hazen made his own
camera obscura
海桑亲自做出了他的暗箱
and dazzled the caliphs.
令哈里发们赞叹不已
A camera obscura works best
in bright light.
有效的暗箱需要明亮的光线
The stars of the night sky
are way too dim for this.
夜空中的星光对它来说太暗淡了
We somehow need a bigger
opening to collect light,
我们需要更大的孔来收集光线
but we also need
to maintain focus.
同时我们需要保持焦点
A telescope collects light
望远镜从视野的
from any spot
in its field of view
各个角度收集光线
across the entire lens
or mirror,
遍布整个镜片或者镜子
an opening much larger
than the camera obscura hole.
开孔要比照相机暗箱的小孔大许多
This is one
of the first telescopes...
这是最早的望远镜之一
the one that Galileo looked
through in 1609.
伽利略在1609年使用过的那个
With it, he pulled aside
the heavy curtain of night
他用这个掀开了黑夜的厚重幕布
and began to discover
the cosmos.
并且开始发现宇宙
The lens made it possible
都归功于镜片
for a telescope to have a much
larger light-collecting area
镜片为望远镜提供了比我们眼睛
than our eyes have.
更大的光线收集区域
Big buckets catch more rain
than small ones.
大桶比小桶可以收集更多的雨水
Modern telescopes have larger
collecting areas,
现代的望远镜拥有更大收集区域
highly sensitive detectors,
高度敏感的探测器
and they track the same object
for hours at a time
并可以长时间锁定同一目标
to accumulate as much
of its light as possible.
以搜集尽可能多的光线
Space-based telescopes
such as the Hubble,
像哈勃 这样的太空望远镜
have captured light
from the most distant
搜集来自最久远星系的
and ancient galaxies,
光线
giving us vastly clearer
pictures of the cosmos.
为我们带来大量的更清晰的宇宙图片
Al-Hazen discovered how images
are formed by light,
海桑发现了光线成像的原理
but that was far
from his greatest achievement.
但这并不是他最最伟大的成就
Ibn al-Hazen was the first
person ever
他是有史以来设定
to set down
the rules of science.
科学原则的第一人
He created
an error-correcting mechanism,
他创造了一套纠错机制
a systematic and relentless way
一套系统的 严格的
to sift out misconceptions
in our thinking.
审查错误观念的机制
Finding truth is difficult...
探究真相是困难的
and the road to it is rough.
探究真相的道路是崎岖的
As seekers after truth,
作为追寻真相的人
you will be wise to withhold
judgment and not simply put
不轻易下判断 不轻信古人所云
your trust in the writings
of the ancients.
是十分明智的
You must question and critically
examine those writings
你必须质疑并且谨慎的验证这些理论
from every side.
从各个角度
You must submit only
to argument and experiment
你只能接受论据和实验的结果
and not to the sayings
of any person.
而不是别人的说法
For every human being
is vulnerable
因为每个人都有弱点
to all kinds of imperfection.
没有人是完美的
As seekers after truth,
作为寻求真相的人
we must also suspect
and question
我们必须怀疑并质疑
our own ideas as we perform
our investigations,
我们自己的理论  反复论证
to avoid falling into prejudice
or careless thinking.
避免陷入偏见与疏忽
Take this course, and truth
will be revealed to you.
接受这些方针  真相就在眼前
This is the method of science.
这就是科学的方式
So powerful that it's carried
our robotic emissaries
得益于此 我们的机器人大使可以
to the edge of
the solar system and beyond.
航行到太阳系的边缘乃至无限的宇宙
It has doubled our lifespan,
它扩展了我们的生命长度
made the lost worlds
of the past
将过去的失落世界
come alive.
带回现在
Science has enabled us
to predict events
科学使我们可以对遥远的未来
in the distant future...
做出预测
and to communicate with each
other at the speed of light,
让我们可以彼此以光速交流
as I am with you,
right at this moment.
就像你我之间  此时此刻
This way of thinking
has given us powers
这种思考的方式带给我们力量
that al-Hazen himself
would have regarded as wizardry.
那种海桑都认为神奇的力量
But it was he who put us
on this rough, endless road.
他将我们带上这条崎岖 无尽的道路
And now it has taken us
to a place
将我们带到一个地方
where even light itself
is enshrouded in darkness.
在那里即使光线也被黑暗掩盖
Light has properties unlike
anything else
光线有着独一无二的属性
in the realm
of human existence.
以人类存在的领域来说
Take the speed of light.
比如光的速度
The basic particle of light,
the photon,
光的基础微粒  光子
is born traveling
at the speed of light
当它从原子或分子中诞生时
as it emerges from
an atom or a molecule.
就有光的速度
A photon never knows
any other speed,
也只有这一种速度
and we've not found another
phenomenon that accelerates
我们尚未发现其他任何可以立即
from zero to top speed
instantaneously.
从0加速到速度极限的现象
Nothing else
could move as fast.
没有别的东西可以移动这么快
When we try to accelerate other
particles closer and closer
当我们尝试将其他粒子不断加速
to the speed of light,
they resist more and more,
越接近光速  阻力越大
as though they're getting
heavier and heavier.
并且越来越重
No experiment yet devised
还没有任何实验可以
has ever made a particle
move as fast as light.
将粒子加速到光的速度
What was that?
哪是什么
You hear something?
你听了吗
Where was I? Oh, yeah.
说到哪了 哦 对了
I don't know anything else
in life that behaves like light.
没有什么东西能表现的像光那样
I cannot reconcile
its strange properties
我无法将它的这些奇怪的性质
with everything else
my senses tell me.
与我感知的其他事物协调一致
Our urge to trust
our senses overpowers
我们本能地更加信任我们的感官
what our measuring devices
tell us about
而不愿接受我们的测量仪器
the actual nature of reality.
所告诉我们的现实的确切本质
Our senses work fine
for life-size objects
对于以普通速度运动的普通大小的物体
moving at mammal speeds,
我们的感官没有问题
but are ill-adapted for the
wonderland laws of lightspeed.
但是却不适用于光速那些神奇的规则
We don't even know why
there's a cosmic speed limit.
我们甚至不明白为什么会有宇宙速度极限
Time stands still when you're
traveling at the speed of light.
时间在达到光速时静止
What is light, anyway?
到底什么是光
Isaac Newton's enduring
fascination with light
艾萨克·牛顿始终对光非常着迷
began when he was a child...
从他还是个孩子时
in this very house.
就在这个房子里
By the time he was in his 20s,
Newton became the first person
他在弱冠之年  就是第一位
to decipher the mystery
of the rainbow.
破译彩虹奥秘的人
Newton discovered that some
light, or white light,
牛顿发现有些光  白光
is a mixture of all the colors
of the rainbow.
由所有彩虹的颜色混合而成
Major discovery.
重大的发现
He named the displays of colors
a "spectrum"
他将之称为 光谱
from the Latin for "phantom"
or "apparition."
来源于拉丁语中的幻影 或者幽灵
Begging your pardon,
Master Newton,
牛大师 抱歉打扰了
the cook frets that your dinner
will spoil, sir.
晚饭再不吃就要坏了
No, Isaac, don't
put the magnifying glass down!
哎呀不 艾萨克 别把放大镜放下
Something even more amazing
is hidden in the light--
光里还有更神奇的东西
a code, a key to the cosmos.
密码  通向宇宙的钥匙
Isaac Newton didn't miss much,
but that one was a beaut.
牛顿错过了一项很重要的发现
He just walked right past
the door to a hidden universe;
他错过了那扇通向神秘宇宙的门
a door that would not swing open
again for another 150 years.
那扇门直到150年后才再次开启
It would fall
on another scientist,
归功于另一位科学家
working in the year 1800,
1800年 在工作时
to stumble
on a piece of evidence
无意间发现了一些证据
for the unseen worlds
that surround us.
一个肉眼看不见的世界就在我们周围
By night, William Herschel
scanned the heavens
晚上  威廉·赫歇尔搜索天空
with the largest telescope
of his time.
使用当时最大的望远镜
By day, Herschel performed
experiments.
白天  赫歇尔做实验
From Newton's earlier work,
it was known that sunlight
根据牛顿的研究结果  已知日光
is a blend of different colors.
由不同颜色的光混合而成
And everyone knew,
just from being outside,
所有人都知道  在户外
that sunlight carries heat.
日光带来热量
William Herschel asked
威廉赫歇尔不禁疑问
whether some colors of light
carry more heat than others.
哪种颜色的光带着更多的热量
The nature of scientific genius
is to question
科学天才的天性就是对那些
what the rest of us
take for granted...
我们认为理所当然的事情产生疑问
and then do the experiment.
然后做用实验证实
The thermometer that Herschel
placed outside the spectrum
赫歇尔放在光照范围之外的温度计
was his control.
是他的对照物
The control in any experiment
对照物在实验中
always lacks
the factor being tested.
不参加实验操作
That way, you know
if what you're testing is
这样才能知道你的实验物
really the thing responsible
for the observation.
是否真的是对实验本身产生反应
In Herschel's experiment,
在赫歇尔的试验中
the relationship between
验证的是
color and temperature
was being tested,
颜色和温度的关系
and so his control was
a thermometer
他用一个温度计做对照
over the part
of the white sheet
放在白纸上
that was not illuminated
by sunlight at all.
日光照射之外
There's that sound again.
那个声音又来了
What is that?
到底是什么
Okay, red light is warmer
than blue light.
红光比蓝光产生更多的热
Interesting discovery,
but not exactly revolutionary.
有趣的发现 但还不算惊天动地
No, there's nothing wrong
with your thermometer.
你的温度计没有问题
You've just discovered
a new kind of light.
你只是发现了一种新的光
Herschel was the first
to detect this unseen presence
赫歇尔是首位发现在光谱中
lurking just below
the red end of the spectrum.
红色以外（以下）不可见光的人
That's why it came
to be called "infrared."
这就是红外线名字的由来（infra red）
"Infra" is Latin
for the word "below."
英语的infra在拉丁语中意为 之下
It's invisible.
它不可见
Our eyes are not sensitive
to this kind of light,
我们的眼睛对这类光不敏感
but our skin is--
we feel it as heat.
我们的皮肤不同  我们可以感受到热
Now, that's
a really big discovery.
这才是真正的重大发现
But far greater secrets
were still hiding
但是光线之中依然隐藏着
deep inside the light.
更大的秘密
At about the
same time that William Herschel
几乎与威廉赫歇尔在英格兰
was discovering infrared light
in his parlor in England,
发现红外线的同时
a young boy named
Joseph Fraunhofer
一位名叫约瑟夫·夫琅和费的孩子
was trapped
in hopeless drudgery.
从事着乏味的繁重的工作
He stood over a cauldron
of toxic chemicals
他站在盛满有毒化学物的熔炉旁
and endlessly stirred.
不断地搅拌
Joseph had been orphaned
at the age of 11
约瑟夫11岁时成了孤儿
and given to a harsh master
named Weichselberger,
被送给苛刻的维塞伯格
the royal mirror-maker.
他替皇家做镜子
He prevented Joseph
from going to school.
他不让约瑟夫去上学
Instead, Joseph labored in
而是白天让约瑟夫在玻璃作坊做苦力
the glass-making
workshop by day,
而是白天让约瑟夫在玻璃作坊做苦力
and tended to the master's
household chores by night.
晚上去他家里做家务
Hurry up, stupid!
快点  白痴
And remember, no reading.
记住 不许读书
Until Joseph got his big break.
约瑟夫终于解脱了
Weichselberger's
house collapsed.
维塞伯格的房子塌了
Maximilian, the future
king of Bavaria,
马克西米利安 巴伐利亚未来的国王
hurried to the scene
of the calamity
急忙来到灾难现场
to see if he could help.
向灾民伸出援手
Maximilian was known for
马克西米利安出了名的关心他的臣民
taking an interest
in his subjects,
马克西米利安出了名的关心他的臣民
which was highly unusual
for its time.
这在当年并不寻常
In attracting the concern
of the future king of Bavaria,
在巴伐利亚未来国王的关怀下
young Joseph Fraunhofer
年轻的约瑟夫·夫琅和费
found an aperture into
a different universe.
的未来从此发生了变化
And not just for himself.
而且不仅是他个人
Prince Maximilian
gave Joseph money
马克西米利亚王子资助约瑟夫
and asked his privy councilor
并让他的高级顾问
to provide further
help to the boy,
向这孩子提供更多的帮助
should it be needed.
提供所需的一切
Weichselberger continued
to exploit him
维塞伯格还在剥削他
and prevent him
from attending school.
不让他去学校
But the prince's councilor
intervened,
但是在王子顾问的干预下
offering Joseph a position
at the Optical Institute.
约瑟夫进入了光学学院
This small gesture of kindness
really paid off.
这小小的善举带来了非常丰厚的回报
By the time he was 27,
在他27岁时
Joseph Fraunhofer was
the world's leading designer
约瑟夫·夫琅和费成为了首屈一指的设计师
of high-quality lenses,
从优质的镜片
telescopes and other
optical instruments.
到望远镜和其他光学器材
His firm was housed here,
in the old Benediktbeuren Abbey.
他的工厂位于本讷迪克特伯伊昂修道院
In the early 19th century,
在19世纪上半叶
this was top-secret,
ultra-high technology.
这可是绝密的 超级的高科技
The Benedictine monks
of earlier times
早期的本笃会修道士们
had taken a vow of secrecy.
都要经过保密宣誓
This local tradition,
这种当地的风俗
and the ability
to restrict access
加上夫琅和费实验室
to Fraunhofer's laboratory,
严格的通行制度
allowed him to maintain control
让他可以持续掌控
of trade and state secrets.
这些机密
Fraunhofer was experimenting
with prisms
夫琅和费在实验中使用棱镜
to find the best types of glass
for precision lenses.
来寻找制作精密镜片的最佳玻璃
How, he wondered,
could he get a better look
怎样才能更好的观察
at the spectrum that
a prism produced?
棱镜产生的光谱呢
Friedrich, bring me
the theodolite, please.
弗雷德里希 请把经纬仪拿来
Okay, while Fraunhofer
sets up his theodolite--
在夫琅和费安装经纬仪的时候
it's a kind of telescope--
经纬仪是某种望远镜
I want to show you something
in another part of the abbey.
我带你看看修道院的其他地方
Sound waves are
so beautiful to hear.
声波听上去如此动人
Imagine how beautiful
they'd be to see.
想象一下 会有多迷人如果我们能看到它
You ever wondered why organ
pipes have different lengths?
你想过为什么管风琴的音管长短不一吗
I press a key...
按下一个琴键
it sends compressed air
它将一股压缩空气
into a particular pipe,
送进特定的管道
producing sound waves.
产生声波
If we could slow the sound waves
down a few hundred times,
如果我们可以把声波速度降低几百倍
they would look like this.
它看上去就是这样的
The length of the pipe
管道的长度
determines the length
of the sound wave
决定了可以容纳何种长度的声波
that can fit inside it.
A short pipe gives you
a short sound wave.
短的管道发出短的声波
Short sounds waves have
high pitch, or frequency.
短的声波产生高的音调或者频率
Let's stop the waves
for a better look.
我们把声波停下 仔细看看
The distance between
adjacent waves
相邻波之间的距离
is called the wavelength.
称为 波长
A long pipe gives you
a long sound wave
长管道发出长的声波
with a low pitch,
or low frequency.
低音调 或者低频率
The medieval manuscript of
this music, "Carmina Burana,"
布兰诗歌 这个中世纪作品的手稿
was discovered
in this very abbey.
就是在这间修道院发现的
Sound waves can't travel
through a vacuum.
声波无法在真空中传递
They need matter to ride on,
它们需要传播媒介
like molecules of air,
or water, or rock.
比如空气 水 岩石的分子
But light waves fly solo.
但光不需要
They can move
through empty space.
它们可以在太空中穿行
And fast--
速度很快
a million times faster
than sound waves in air.
比声波在空气中快100万倍
And the wavelengths
of the light we see
我们看到的光的波长
are so much shorter
than sound waves.
比声波的要短得多
About 50,000 light waves
5万个光波
would fit right in here.
就这么长
Oh, yeah.
对了
Fraunhofer.
夫琅和费
Just in time.
时间正好
We didn't miss it.
正好赶上
Just as the wavelength of sound
就如同声音的波长
determines the pitch
that we hear,
决定我们听到的音调
the wavelength of light
光的波长
determines the color
that we see.
决定了我们看到的颜色
But how does a prism
spread out the colors
棱镜是如何将颜色
concealed in
a beam of sunlight?
从一束日光中分开的呢
When light travels
through air or space,
当光穿过空气或太空
all its colors move
at the same speed.
所有的颜色速度保持一致
But when it hits glass
at an angle,
但当它以一个角度照射到玻璃上时
the light slows down
and changes direction.
光慢下来 并改变了方向
Inside the prism,
在棱镜内
each color moves
at a different speed.
不同的颜色以不用的速度移动
In glass, violet light,
在玻璃中  蓝紫色
which is carried by
the shortest waves we see,
由我们看到的最短的光波产生
slows down more than red light,
速度比红光还慢
which has the longest waves.
红光的光波最长
These changes in speed
速度的改变
pry the colors apart,
将不同颜色分开
sending their waves off
把它们的光波发散到
in slightly different
directions.
稍微不同的方向
That's how a prism works.
这就是棱镜的原理
If I seem unduly
emotional about this,
如果我等会情绪失控
it's because Joseph Fraunhofer
is about to do
都是因为约瑟夫·夫琅和费将要做的
what Isaac Newton
could've done, but didn't.
是牛顿可以做 却没有做的
And it'll have a powerful effect
它将带来深远的影响
on the course of my own life.
对我自身来说
You are witnessing the marriage
你见证的是
of physics and astronomy,
物理学和天文学的结合
the birth of my own
field of science,
我研究的这个领域的诞生
astrophysics.
天体物理学
Written in the light,
记录在光线中
in those vertical black lines...
在那些垂直的黑线中的
is secret code.
是神秘的密码
Fraunhofer looked at them,
and wondered...
夫琅和费看着它们 自忖道
Why?
为什么
A code that comes to us
从外太空传来的密码
from an alien universe.
What is the message
这些黑色的竖线包含怎样的信息呢
written in these dark,
vertical lines?
这些黑色的竖线包含怎样的信息呢
It took a hundred years
of thinking,
人们花费了上百年去思考
questioning, searching
to decipher it.
探询 调查 破译
Lovely, isn't it?
很妙吧
Why?
为什么
There are many layers to
the fine structure of beauty...
美丽的精细结构由许多层次组成
the chemistry of the Earth
and its atmosphere...
地球的化学成分 和它的大气层
the evolution of life...
生命的进化
Many distinct threads.
独特的脉络
Let's just examine one,
at the surface...
我们就在表面挑一个观察
the colors of nature
that dazzle us.
令我们惊叹的大自然的颜色
What's really happening?
到底是什么
How does the red, the blue...
这些红色  蓝色
the astonishing palette
of nature's colors...
简直就是大自然的神奇调色盘
how do they happen?
怎么产生的
Light waves of different lengths
from the Sun
太阳发出不同长度的光波
strike the Earth.
射到地球
The petals of these
particular flowers
这些花的花瓣
absorb all the low-energy,
吸收所有低能量的
long red wavelengths of light.
长的红色光波
But the petals reflect
但是花瓣反射
the shorter, high-energy
blue wavelengths.
短的 高能量的 蓝色光波
That interaction
between starlight and petal--
星光与花瓣
or water, or Van Gogh--
与水 或与梵高的互动
is what makes blue.
产生了 蓝色
The longest waves,
最长的光波
the ones we see as red,
我们所看到的红色
have the lowest energy.
有着最低的能量
Color is the way
our eyes perceive
颜色是我们的眼睛
how energetic light waves are.
分辨光波能量的方式
A sunset...
日落
a flag...
旗帜
the eyes of your beloved...
情人的眼睛
that shiny new car.
闪亮的新车
The feelings they inspire
它们带来的灵感
happen when something inside you
激发你内在的某些东西
is triggered by
a particular variation
由一种特殊的变化产生
in the frequency and
energy of light waves.
光波的能量与频率的变化
And the secret message?
神秘的信息
Those black vertical lines
那些黑色竖线
in Fraunhofer's spectrum?
夫琅和费在光谱中看到的
What makes them?
它们怎么产生的
They occur when the light waves
它们产生于 某些特定颜色
of those particular colors
are being absorbed.
的光波被吸收时
It happens on another level
of reality,
那是发生在另一个层面的事情
far smaller than the world
we're used to operating in.
比我们身处的这个世界小的多得多
To get there,
we'll need to become
要去那里 我们必须变得
ten billion times smaller
than we are.
比现在小100亿倍
We could pick
any one of these atoms.
我们可以从这些原子中任选一个
But let's go
for the hydrogen atom.
还是选氢原子吧
The hydrogen atom is
the most plentiful kind
氢原子是宇宙中
of atom in the cosmos.
最普遍的一种
And the simplest.
最简单的
It has only one electron.
只有一个电子
And only one proton.
只有一个质子
We've entered
the quantum realm.
我们进入了量子领域
It doesn't correspond
这并不符合
to ordinary human experience.
通常的经验
Common sense is
no help here at all.
常识在这里不起作用
Take the hydrogen atom's
electron, for example.
以氢原子的电子为例
In an atom, an electron
在原子中 电子
doesn't exist between orbitals.
不存在于轨道之间
It disappears from one orbital
它从一个轨道消失
and reappears in another.
又在另一个轨道出现
It's as if you took an elevator
from the second floor
就像你坐电梯从2楼去4楼
to the fourth floor,
but ceased to exist in between.
却凭空消失
And another thing.
还有
Quantum elevators only stop
at certain floors.
量子电梯并不会停在特定的楼层
The sizes of the electron
orbits are strictly limited,
电子的轨道尺寸有着严格的限制
and different
for the atoms of every element.
每种元素的原子都不相同
That's why the elements
are different.
这就是元素各不相同的原因
The chemistry
of anything is determined
所有物质的化学属性都由它的电子的轨道决定
by its electron orbits.
The force that holds
an electron in orbit
将电子束缚在轨道上的力量
has nothing to do with gravity.
和重力没有丝毫关系
It's a force
of electrical attraction.
它是电气引力
The electron dances a wavy ring
电子沿着波浪形的圆环
around the central nucleus
of a hydrogen atom.
环绕氢原子的原子核运行
And makes quantum leaps
from orbit to orbit.
从一个轨道跳到另一个轨道
Up or down.
忽上忽下
The larger the orbit,
轨道越大
the greater the energy
of an electron.
电子的能量越大
An electron has
电子必须获取能量才能跳跃到更大的轨道上
to get energy to leap
to a larger orbit.
And it has to lose energy
to jump back down.
然后必须释放能量才能跳回来
Every upward leap
is caused by...
每次向上的跳跃都是原子吸收光波的结果
an atom absorbing a light wave.
But we have no idea what causes
the downward leaps.
我们还不知道是什么使它向下跳跃
What we do know that such leaps
always produce a light wave
我们只知道向下跳跃产生光波
whose color matches
the energy difference
这种光波的颜色与轨道间的能量差异相吻合
between the orbitals.
The Sun's surface radiates
light waves of all colors.
太阳的表面辐射出所有颜色的光波
If you look at sunlight
through a prism,
如果你透过棱镜看日光
you'll see its spectrum.
你能看到它的光谱
When you magnify the spectrum
with a telescope,
当你用望远镜放大光谱时
as Joseph Fraunhofer did,
就像约瑟夫·夫琅和费那样
you raise the curtain
你就可以窥视
on the electron dance
within the atom.
电子在原子中跳跃的真相
When the energy
of the electron flags,
当电子的能量衰弱
and it drops
to a lower orbital,
它降到较低的轨道时
the light wave
it emits scatters.
光波逸散
Most of it doesn't reach us.
大多数不会到我们这里
That leaves a dark gap
这就留下了一个黑暗的空当
or black vertical line
in the spectrum.
或者说 光谱中的黑色竖线
These dark lines
are the shadows
这些黑线就是
cast by hydrogen atoms
氢原子在太阳大气层中造成的阴影
in the atmosphere of the Sun.
Sodium atoms cast
different shadows.
钠原子发出不同的阴影
Their electrons dance
to a different tune.
他们的电子按照不同的曲子跳舞
A grain of table salt
is composed
一粒盐由钠原子和氯原子组成
of sodium and chlorine atoms.
Ten million billion of them
千万亿的原子疯狂地舞动
doing their crazy dances
in a single grain of salt.
仅仅是在一粒盐中
And a single iron atom
with 26 electrons
一个铁原子有26个电子
is like a great
big production number
庞大的宛如百老汇音乐剧的制作团队
in a Broadway musical.
When you look at a star
with a spectroscope,
当你用分光仪观察星星时
you see the dark lines
from all the elements
在它大气层中所有元素上都能看到黑线
in its atmosphere.
Show me the spectrum
of anything,
给我任意一个物体的光谱
whether here on Earth
or from a distant star,
不论是在地球上的 还是在遥远的星星上
and I'll tell you
what it's made of.
我都可以告诉你 它的元素构成
Fraunhofer's lines are
the atomic signatures
夫琅和费线是元素的原子签名
of the elements writ large
across the cosmos.
遍布整个宇宙
As with every
other major revelation
如同科学历史上的
in the history of science,
it opened the way
其他重大发现一样  它带来了
to newer and deeper mysteries.
更新更深层次的谜团
And to the revelation
that there were
还有更多的
many more secrets
hiding in the light.
秘密依然藏在光线中
When Joseph Fraunhofer combined
a prism with a telescope
当夫琅和费把望远镜和棱镜结合在一起
and turned it toward the skies,
用它们探索天空
he brought the stars
much closer to us.
他将星星与我们之间的距离缩短了
When he was only 39,
他39岁时
he contracted a fatal illness.
身患重病
Perhaps as a result of his
early and long-term exposure
可能是由于早年长期曝露在
to the toxic chemicals
of glassmaking.
制作玻璃的有毒化学物质的缘故
You never know where
the next genius will come from.
你永远不知道下一个天才在何处诞生
How many of them do we leave
in the rubble?
不知道我们错过了多少天才
The prince and his kingdom
were immeasurably enriched
对一位孤儿的善行给王子
by that act of kindness
to a poor orphan.
和他的王国带来不可计量的财富
Fraunhofer's discoveries
transformed Bavaria
夫琅和费的发现将巴伐利亚
from a rural backwater
to a technological powerhouse.
从偏僻的乡下变成高科技的制造中心
As he lay dying,
the government was desperate
在他弥留之际  政府急切地
to preserve every shred
of his precious knowledge
想要保留他所有的关于
about the high technology
of optical glass.
高科技光学玻璃的宝贵知识
But it could only be divulged
to a person
但这只能让一个人知道
with top security clearance--
此人有着最高级别的涉密权限
the director of the mint.
铸币局主管
The government kept
Fraunhofer's technology
政府保留了夫琅和费的技术
for making perfect
optical glass
用于制造完美的光学玻璃
a State secret
for another hundred years.
一个上百年的国家机密
This would prove
to be a major obstacle
后来证明这给某人带来很大的阻碍
for someone we'll meet later
in our journey.
以后我们会提到
But Fraunhofer would allow
no such secrecy
但夫琅和费不能容忍这样
where his pure scientific
research was concerned.
对他的科学研究保密
He knew that science requires
openness to flourish;
他知道科学需要开放才能昌盛
that our understanding of nature
belongs to the world.
我们对于自然的了解属于全世界
As soon as Fraunhofer discovered
the spectral lines,
夫琅和费发现谱线后
he published everything
he knew about them.
他立即发表了所有的成果
And the reverberations
of his momentous discovery
如此重要的发现带来的影响
echo still.
持续至今
His spectral lines revealed
that the visible cosmos
他的谱线揭示了可观测的宇宙
is all made
of the same elements.
是由相同的元素构成
The planets...
行星们
The stars...
恒星们
The galaxies...
星系们
We, ourselves,
and all of life...
我们  还有所有的生命体
The same star stuff.
拥有共同的物质
He made it possible
for us to know
他让我们知道了
what's in the atmosphere
of other worlds.
其他星球的大气层中有些什么
And in galaxies millions
of light-years away.
远在上百万光年外的星系中
Spectral lines revealed
not only the composition
谱线不止揭示了遥远物体的成分
of far-off objects,
but also their motion
也揭示了它们是在靠近还是远离我们
towards or away from us.
Using them, we discovered
that our universe is expanding.
通过它 我们发现我们的宇宙还在扩张
But perhaps the greatest
revelation of spectroscopy
但光谱学带给我们的最大启示可能是
is the discovery
of the thing it cannot see.
发现了根本就看不见的物质
A hidden universe
of dark matter
由暗物质组成的隐蔽宇宙
six times more massive
than the familiar cosmos.
质量比我们熟悉的宇宙超出6倍
It's made
of some mysterious substance
由某些神秘的物质组成
that does not emit, reflect
or absorb any kind of light.
不会发出 反射或者吸收任何形式的光
We only know it's there
because of its gravity,
因为它的引力我们才知道它的存在
which pulls on all the galaxies
它的引力吸引着星系
and speeds up the visible stars within them.
并为其中的恒星加速
There are many more kinds of
light than our eyes can see.
我们的眼睛可以看见很多种类的光
Confining our perception
of nature to visible light
认为我们的自然只有可见光
is like listening to music
就如同听的音乐
in only one octave.
只有一个八度
There are so many more.
其实还有很多很多
They differ only in wavelength,
它们仅仅是波长的区别
but over a huge range.
只是范围很大
For instance, infrared light...
比如 红外线
the kind that William Herschel discovered
威廉·赫歇尔发现的那种
Or X-ray light.
X光
Or radio light.
无线电波
Or in gamma-ray light.
伽马射线
These are not just different
ways of seeing the same thing.
不仅是看东西的方式不同
These other kinds of light
不同的光
reveal different objects
and phenomena in the cosmos.
揭示出宇宙中不同的物体和现象
In gamma-ray light, for example,
we can see mysterious explosions
比方说通过伽马射线 我们可以看到
遥远星系的神秘爆炸
in distant galaxies
that we would otherwise miss.
否则就可能错过
And in microwave light,
we can see all the way back
通过微波 我们可以看到
to the birth of the universe.
宇宙诞生之初的情景
We have only just opened our eyes.
我们只不过 刚刚睁开眼睛
Sync and corrections by n17t01
www.addic7ed.com
中文翻译：@SaltyEggPain